你有 ever felt like
like the universe is just
personally specifically
out to get your wallet
哦, absolutely, all the time
right, like there's this
I don't know, cosmic conspiracy
focused entirely on your specific brokerage account
yeah, they're washing you
Exactly
你, you, you finally pull the trigger
you buy the stock
you've been watching for months
and literally the minute your order executes
the price just plummet
to completely tanks
it falls right off a cliff
yeah, so, you know, you sweat it out
for a few days, the anxiety builds
and finally you just panic sell
to stop the bleeding
and we all know what happens next
instantly it skyrockets
the very next morning
or like maybe you see this with sports
you're betting on your absolute favorite team
a team that has been dominating
the entire season
and the one time you put actual money on the line
they miraculously lose to the worst team in the league
so today we are doing a deep dive
into the behavioral economics
behind this whole phenomenon
we really want to figure out exactly
why our brains are just
well, hardwired to sabotage our own wallets
and more importantly, how we can build systems
to outsmart ourselves
it's such a universally frustrating experience
and I think the most important thing
to establish right out of the gate
is that this is not about bad luck
it's really not
no, not at all
you are not cursed
the market doesn't know you exist
I promise
it's a little humbling
but good to know
right
what you're actually experiencing
is a series of incredibly predictable psychological traps
that honestly almost everyone falls into
okay, so it's a human thing, not a me thing
exactly
by the time we finish unpacking these sources today
you're going to understand the invisible cognitive forces
that are driving your most irrational financial decisions
I can't wait
yeah, it basically all comes down to
how the human brain
processes information, assesses risk
and fundamentally misinterprets reality
when you know, when actual money is on the line
well, I think
to really understand how we react to losing money
we first need to look at how our brains perceive reality
in the first place
like why are we so convinced
that losing is just the default state of affairs in the market
it's a great question
because I mean, if you look at a chart of the S&P 500
over the last 50 years
it generally just goes up into the right
yet everyone feels like they're constantly losing
yeah, that disconnect
it comes down to two major cognitive biases
and the first one is called the availability heuristic
availability heuristic
okay, right
to really understand this
you have to look at the information ecosystem we live in
I mean, think about media outlets
financial news networks
social media algorithms
they're all trying to grab your attention
exactly, they're heavily incentivized to drive engagement
and well, nothing drives engagement quite like fear
oh, totally, doom scrolling is a real thing
it is
because our brains are evolutionarily wired
to pay attention to threats
so you're constantly bombarded with these stories
highlighting massive market crashes
retail investors losing everything
or impending economic doom
right, this guy is always falling
always
and because this negative information
is so highly available to your brain on a daily basis
your mind naturally substitutes the frequency
of those headlines
for the actual probability of reality
oh wow
yeah, it tricks you into thinking
that devastating losses are the absolute norm
meanwhile, that slow, boring, upward trend of the market
it barely registers because it doesn't trigger any kind of survival response
that makes so much sense
I mean nobody is clicking on a headline that says
market slowly and predictably grew by a fraction of a percent this week
right, no one cares
there's no dopamine hit there, no adrenaline
exactly
and that constant negative framing
it sets the stage for the second trap
which is confirmation bias
okay, how does that one work here
well, because you've been subconsciously
primed to expect failure by this whole media environment
your brain starts doing this really fascinating filtering process
like blocking things out
yeah, it acts like a bouncer at a club
and it only lets an information that validates the idea
that the market is super dangerous
so investors will actively but unconsciously
selectively remember their agonizing losses
and just completely filter out their mundane gains
so they're literally rewriting their own history
yes
it reinforces this totally false personalized narrative of the moment I buy
it drops
you remember the pain of the drop
and you just discard the five other times
you made a modest profit
because well, they don't fit the narrative
you know this reminds me so much of being stuck in traffic
oh yeah
like when you're in a massive rush to get to an appointment
you only ever remember hitting every single red light
it feels personal
yes
you sit there fuming
feeling like the city planners designed the entire grid
specifically to ruin your day
but you completely forget all the times you just sailed right through four green lights in a row
because you don't even notice them
exactly the green lights don't trigger any emotional response
but the red lights completely validate your existing frustration and stress
your brain just discarded the green lights as irrelevant data
that is a perfect analogy
the red lights or the financial losses
are emotionally salient they just stick to your memory
but what is truly fascinating is that once we understand that our brains are
selectively highlighting these negative events
we really have to ask why those specific negative events hurt so deeply
right why are they so sticky
it's not just a matter of remembering them more often
they actually cause a disproportionate level of psychological distress
and this brings us to the underlying mathematics of our emotional pain
the math of emotional pain
that sounds incredibly bleak
doesn't a bit dark
how do we actually quantify the feeling of losing money
so this was basically the life's work of two behavioral economists
Daniel Kahneman and Amos Tversky
they introduced a concept that essentially defines modern behavioral finance
which is known as loss of version
loss of version
right
through extensive research
they discovered that the psychological reality of financial pain
is not at all balanced with financial joy
so it's not a one-to-one ratio
not even close
in fact the pain you feel from a financial loss is mathematically two to three times
more intense than the joy you feel from an equivalent game
wait really so like finding a hundred dollar bill on the sidewalk
gives you a certain baseline amount of pleasure
but losing a hundred dollar bill out of your pocket
generates two to three times as much psychological agony
that is the exact ratio
that's crazy
it is
but it actually makes perfect sense when you look at it through the lens of evolutionary biology
I'll take it back to the cavemen
always
for our hunter-gatherer ancestors the consequences of losing were much much more
severe than the benefits of gaining
also
well if you missed out on finding an extra berry bush you might be hungry for a
day
but if you lost your only food supply or your only weapon
you died
right it's life or death
exactly
human beings evolved to treat losses as existential threats
the alarm bells in your brain are designed to ring three times louder for a loss
than a game
which is great for outrunning a predator but
terrible for investing completely terrible
in modern times that evolutionary survival mechanism totally short circuits are
investing
it's the core reason you panic and sell early
the moment your portfolio drops even slightly
your brain thinks the stock dipping is a physical threat yes
your brain is screaming at you to stop the pain
treating a five percent dip in a stock like I don't know
a tiger wrestling in the bushes
okay I have to push back on this just a little bit
because if loss aversion is so deeply hardwired into our biology
and we genuinely hate the feeling of losing two to three times more than we enjoy
winning
why do we ever voluntarily keep playing that's the big question right
more specifically
why doesn't that intense fear of losing
stop people from doubling down on bad bets
you see it all the time someone loses money and instead of running away to protect
themselves for more pain
they bet even more aggressively to try and win it back
shouldn't loss aversion make them just stop entirely
that is the ultimate paradox of behavioral finance
and it's a brilliant point to bring up the reason we double down is actually
because of how loss aversion warps our risk tolerance
okay explain that
well when we're in the positive when our portfolio is up
we tend to become very risk averse
we sell our winning stocks entirely too early because we want to lock in the
gain and avoid the pain of watching a trot
right taking profits too soon
but when we are in the negative the math flips
the agony of the existing loss is so unbearable that we shift from being
risk averse to wildly risk seeking
because we are just desperate to get back to zero
yes it's often called the break even effect
we aren't doubling down because we rationally think it's a good investment
we're doubling down because our brain is treating the realized loss
as an ongoing physical injury
and we just want the bleeding to stop
exactly we will take massive irrational risks just to make the pain stop
we aren't chasing veins anymore
we are running from the finality of the loss
man and because that emotional pain is so severe
it feels like our brains are just constantly scanning their horizon
desperately trying to predict the future to protect us from the next draw
like we want a warning system
you do we absolutely crave certainty in an uncertain environment
so we look for patterns to protect ourselves
but in doing so we end up trapping ourselves in completely contradictory
logical fallacies
well guilty of this I know it
we all are our pattern recognition software is incredibly flawed
when we apply it to complex systems like markets
and to see just how flawed it is
you really just have to contrast to opposing biases
the gambler's fallacy and the hot hand fallacy
okay so the gambler's fallacy
that's the idea that something is due to happen right
like a course correction
correct
it's the belief that if a stock rises for three consecutive days
it is somehow mysteriously due to drop on the four
like the universe owes it a drop
right
but the reality of a highly efficient market is that short-term movements
are largely independent events much like flipping a coin
okay
if you flip a fair coin and it lands on heads three times in a row
the odds of tails on the next flip are still exactly fifty fifty
the coin doesn't have a memory
it doesn't know it just landed on heads exactly
the universe does not keep a cosmic ledger that demands balance in the short term
the market doesn't owe you a drop just because it went up
but because we feel like a drop is coming
we sell early
yes
this false feeling of an impending correction leads people to sell their assets
entirely too prematurely
the fabricated phantom drop in their heads
and sell to protect themselves from it
beautifully put but then you have the complete opposite cognitive trap
the hot hand fallacy which is what this is the belief that a winning streak
practically guarantees continued winning
you see a tech stock double in a month
and instead of thinking it is due for a correction
you assume the momentum will just last forever and you buy in at the absolute peak
the irony of all this is that the exact same investor
will commit both of these contradictory fallacies in different scenarios
without ever realizing the hypocrisy in their own logic
the sheer mental gymnastics required to hold both of those beliefs is staggering
it really is
so let me get this straight
my brain tells me a coin that flipped heads three times is definitely going to be
tails next because it has to balance out
but if a basketball player hits three three pointers in a row
they are definitely going to hit the fourth because they have the hot hand
that's the logic
how does our brain justify using completely opposite frameworks depending on
just what we're looking at
well it justifies it by desperately seeking a narrative of control
right with the coin flip we view it as a mechanical system
we intuitively understand its random
so we impose our human desire for fairness and equilibrium onto it
we expect the universe to balance the scales
okay and the basketball player
with the basketball player or you know the skyrocketing tech startup
we assign human skill or intrinsic momentum to the equation
we think someone is driving the bus exactly
we convince ourselves that the randomness has been overwritten by talent
or exceptional circumstances
we switch our logical framework based on whatever narrative makes us feel like we
have successfully predicted an unpredictable
environment
which brings up a really fascinating dynamic
because this desperate need to find patterns and predict the unpredictable
it isn't just limited to staring at abstract stock charts
oh definitely not
it gets significantly more dangerous when we add tribalism personal passion
and emotional investment into the mix like sports
it does and the research into world cup betting perfectly illustrates just how
toxic this combination can be
I can only imagine
yeah when fans start betting on their absolute favorite soccer teams
all objective rational evaluation just goes completely out the window
they can't see street
they aren't just analyzing statistics anymore
they are projecting their identity onto the outcome
love makes us blind even when we are putting our life savings on the line
so true fans will drastically overestimate their own team's strength
and simultaneously underestimate the opponents
but the deeper psychological concept driving this behavior
is what behavioral economists call the illusion of control
the illusion of control
what exactly is creating that illusion in a sports fan
it's the false belief that acquiring information is the same thing as acquiring
oh that's interesting
think about the modern sports fan
they can spend hours analyzing the starting line-ups
studying the historical win-loss records
looking at advanced metrics and reading expert commentary
doing their homework
right and because they've consumed so much data
they develop a profound sense of expertise
they genuinely feel they have the ability to
accurately predict the outcome of the match
but they don't
not at all
what they are entirely ignoring is the massive undeniable role of randomness
luck and chance
yeah sports are chaotic
exactly
in a soccer match
a single bad bounce of a ball off a goal post
a sudden downpour
or one questionable referee call changes the entire outcome
but the sheer volume of data the fan consumed
gives them a sense of control over a system that is inherently chaotic
i have like the perfect image for this
let's hear it
this illusion of control
it's exactly like when you're a kid playing a racing video game
and your younger sibling wants to play too
oh i know where this is going
to keep them quiet you hand them a second controller
but you leave it completely unplugged
i think every older sibling knows that maneuver
right and the younger sibling sits there
furiously matching the buttons
laying their entire body into the turns
getting incredibly emotionally invested
yeah they really feel it
they genuinely believe
that their specific actions are controlling the car on the screen
and that is exactly what we're doing when we overanalyze this stuff
it really is
we believe that reading a few stats on a sports app
or drawing a few resistance lines on a stock chart
gives us actual
tangible control over a chaotic sporting event
or a global financial market
we're literally just mashing an unplugged controller
that analogy captures the mechanics perfectly
we are mashing buttons on an unplugged controller
and here is where the confirmation bias loops back in
oh how so
when the car on the screen happens to turn left
right as we press the left button
our brain lights up and says
see i did that my analysis was right
oh my gosh yes
we validate our false sense of agency
while ignoring the 99 other times we pressed a button
and absolutely see nothing happened
we just filter out the misses
we confuse correlation with causation
largely because acknowledging our own powerlessness
is just deeply uncomfortable
okay so taking a step back
this is all incredibly humbling
it's meant to be
we've established that our brains are fundamentally rigged
for financial self-sapotage
i mean we have selective memories driven by fear
we experience disproportionate pain that causes us to panic
or chase losses
we use completely contradictory logic to find patterns
that don't exist
and we suffer from a pathetic illusion of control
it's a pretty good summary
we are basically walking cognitive disasters
when it comes to money
so what is the actual antidote to our own human nature
how do we break this cycle
well the path forward requires a complete shift
in how you manage your resources
and the very first step which frankly is often the hardest
particularly for highly educated or high achieving people
is to humbly openly admit your own irrationality
you have to admit you have a problem
exactly
you cannot fix a cognitive bias
if your ego refuses to believe you're susceptible to it
you have to accept that your gut intuition regarding money
is statistically likely to be wrong
so step one is recognizing that you are the unplugged controller
yes and once you admit that
you realize that you must replace your faulty emotional decision-making
with rigid mechanical systems
what kind of systems
a primary example of this is a strategy like dollar cost averaging
okay this basically means you commit to investing a fixed amount of money
at regular predetermined intervals say every two weeks
regardless of what the market is doing
just automatically yes if the market is hitting all-time highs the system buys
if the market is crashing and the news is terrifying
the system buys you completely remove the emotional burden of trying to time the market
which naturally neutralizes both the gambler's fallacy
and the hot hand fallacy exactly because you are no longer deciding if a stock is due
for a drop or writing a hot streak
you aren't making a choice at all
you are systematically removing the human element from the execution
yes and furthermore to protect this system
you need to drastically reduce the frequency of your exposure to the data
meaning stop checking my phone
you have to stop checking your portfolio every single day
but it's so hard
I know but because every time you look you are giving the availability
heuristic and loss of version another chance to hijack your amygdala
that makes sense
if you look at a portfolio daily
you will see a tremendous amount of volatility and red days
which triggers that two to three times pain multiplier we discussed
it's just unnecessary stress
but if you look at it say once a year
you are much more likely to see the broader upward trend
which keeps you calm
it completely changes the entire perspective
are there any specific mechanics or strategies we need to actively avoid
yes the most critical mechanism to avoid is leverage
which is borrowing money to invest
that sounds risky just on the surface
it is when you use leverage you are mathematically amplifying your returns
but you're also severely accelerating your losses
if you put up $1,000 and borrow $9,000
a mere 10% drop in the asset wipes out your entire actual capital
wow just gone in a flash
gone but honestly worse than the math is the psychological impact
leverage acts as a massive amplifier for loss of version
because the stakes are so much higher
exactly
the panic threshold that normally takes weeks to reach
can be breached in minutes when borrowed money is on the line
it completely shatters your ability to remain objective
and stick to a long-term horizon
so if I'm distilling this down for everyone listening
the ultimate secret to winning this game is to literally fire yourself
from the job of managing your own money on a daily basis
fire yourself I like that
because you are fundamentally unqualified for the task
mostly because of your own biology
so instead of trying to just whitenuck your way through the anxiety
you need to build a system that operates like an autopilot on an airplane
great analogy
right when the plane hits heavy turbulence
a human pilot might panic over correct and cause a disaster
but the autopilot doesn't feel fear
it just executes the math keeps the wings level
and flies right through the storm
you just have to take your hands off the controls
and let the system fly the plane
that is the perfect way to frame it
by taking your hands off the yoke
you protect your financial future from its absolute greatest threat
which is your own instincts
well to wrap things up we have covered some incredibly vital ground today
in this deep dive
we really have
we've learned that the agonizing feeling of
I buy and it drops I sell and it rises
isn't a curse
it's really just the predictable result
of media-driven confirmation bias
the evolutionary math of loss of version
contradictory logical fallacies
and our desperate illusion of control
thank you so much for guiding us through this cognitive mind field
it really completely changes how I view
my own reactions to the market
it's a critical topic and i'm really glad we could explore the mechanics behind it
but i do want to leave you with one final lingering question to ponder
long after this deep dive ends
oh leave us with a cliffhanger
well we've established today that admitting we are hopelessly irrational
is the only true path to financial success and that we have to build mechanical systems
to protect ourselves from our own minds
but it makes you wonder
if trusting our gut intuition is mathematically proven to be our absolute worst enemy when it comes to money
well how many of our biggest most profound life choices
like the people we choose to marry or the specific career paths we decide to pursue
are secretly being driven by these exact same logical fallacies